Today's דף daf we pick up at the top of ח עמוד
ב, chet amud bet, so we're a little behind but hopefully it'll
go quickly because so we'll see cause today's דף daf as I
said is ט tet and we've got as you see a lot
of תוספות, tosfot, so it's pretty short, and this section that we're
about to do on ח עמוד ב chet amud bet to catch
up is also like there's a lot of
נוסח nusach of a ברכה beracha or of a תפילה tefilla and
so on. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara is
introducing this idea of ברכת אבלים birchas aveilim which also required a
מנין minyan and the אבלים aveilim were not part of the
מנין. minyan. It also discusses this phenomenon of רחבה, rechava, of the
אבלים aveilim walking back and being left by you know given נחמה
nechama by the people in the two rows like we do and
that was an idea of a מנין minyan and then this סעודת
הבראה, seudat havra'ah, the סעודה seuda that they fed him or her
when they immediately returned in the רחבה rechava in the street, and
all of those various things wasn't exactly clear exactly how the מנין
minyan was different between that סעודת רחבה seudat rechava and the what
the גמרא Gemara called the רחבה rechava in the ברכת המזון, birchat
hamazon, but anyway we will focus on the idea that there clearly
seems to be these ברכת אבלים birchat aveilim in the ברכת המזון.
birchat hamazon. The גמרא Gemara we don't yet know what the נוסח
nusach is. Remember we were just introduced to the נוסח nusach of
the שבע ברכות sheva berachot on the previous דף. daf. So let's
take a look now as the גמרא Gemara continues. The גמרא Gemara
says like this:
where are we exactly?
I'm about to tell you. So
the גמרא Gemara says: well we can pick up from אלא Ela
about seven lines from the top on ח עמוד ב. chet amud
bet. אלא הא דאמר רבי יצחק אמר רבי יוחנן מברכין ברכת חתנים
בעשרה כל שבעה וחתנים מן המנין, Ela ha de'amar Rabbi Yitzchak amar
Rabbi Yochanan mevarachin birchas chatanim b'asara kol shiva vechatanim min haminyan,
that שבע ברכות sheva berachot is the whole ברכת חתנים birchas chatanim
is the whole week and you need ten and the חתנים chatanim
count. ואבלים בברכת אבלים בעשרה כל שבעה ואין אבלים מן המנין, Ve'aveilim
b'birchas aveilim b'asara kol shiva ve'ein aveilim min haminyan, and the ברכה
beracha of the אבלים aveilim you need ten but the אבלים aveilim
don't count because obviously there's a very different role between the מנחמים
menachamim and the אבלים, aveilim, and you do that for the whole
week. So the גמרא Gemara says: ברכת רחבה כל שבעה מי איכא?
birchas rechava kol shiva mi ika? Where do you have a ברכה
beracha of the רחבה rechava like of the meal fed in the
street as it were? So where do you have this idea of
doing it for the whole week? So the גמרא Gemara says: yes
משכחת לה בפנים חדשות, meshkachat lah bipanim chadashot, if same way you
have a פנים חדשות, panim chadashot, new people come during the week
and it adds to the שמחה simcha and therefore you make the
whole שבע ברכות, sheva berachot, new מנחמים menachamim come and there's like
presumably a new opportunity for נחמה nechama and therefore you would do
these ברכת אבלים birchat aveilim for the whole week. Exactly again. What's
the meaning of רחבה? rechava? It's not clear how much that's being
conflated with the point that was said before about ברכת המזון, birchat
hamazon, which means sort of at the end of the meals. So
let's take a look. Okay. The רמב"ם Rambam for example says, the
רמב"ם Rambam interesting he brings out the whole נוסח nusach of the
שבע ברכות sheva berachot in the meals in הלכות ברכות. hilchot berachot.
He does not bring down the נוסח nusach of ברכת אבלים birchat
aveilim which presumably means that even already by his time it was
a little bit out of practice. And he brings out a very
sort of simplified version of it. I'll read it to you or
very what he says in terms of the
נוסח הברכה. nusach haberacha. The רמב"ם Rambam says the following. Hold on.
He says like this. He says: stop it. Hold on.
This thing, it's great but it doesn't always... okay, here it
says: פרק ב Perek Bet in
הלכות ברכות. Hilchot Berachot. וכשמברכין בבית אבל אומר בברכה רביעית. Ukeshe'mevarchin b'veis
avel omer b'beracha revi'is. I think he said אומר. omer. אומר בברכה
רביעית: Omer b'beracha revi'is: המלך החי הטוב והמטיב אל אמת דיין אמת
שופט בצדק שלמית בעולמו לעשות בו
כרצונו שאנחנו עמו ועבדיו
ובכל אנחנו חייבין להודות לו ולברכו.
hamelech hachai hatov vehametiv el emet dayan emet shofet betzedek shalmit b'olamo
la'asot bo kirtzono she'anachnu amo
va'avadav
ubechol anachnu chayavin lehodot lo ulevarcho. So basically you know you add
to הטוב והמטיב hatov vehametiv which was remember על הרוגי ביתר, al
harugei Beitar, a type of a דיין האמת dayan ha'emes type of
a ברכה,
beracha, but phrasing it in a sort of the you know a
positive. That's ברכת... birchat... we had yeah presumably מבקש רחמים על האבל
לנחמו כפי מה שירצה mevakesh rachamim al ha'avel lenachamo kefi mah sheyirtze
and then you say הרחמןs. harachaman So sort of like you know
the הרחמןs harachaman are really after the end of the four ברכות.
berachot. They're really somewhat of an add on. They're not central to
it. Like הרחמן הוא יברך, Harachaman hu yevarech, הרחמן הוא יברך. Harachaman
hu yevarech. So sort of before the הרחמנים harachamans you say your
own words of נחמה nechama to the אבל. avel. That's how the
רמב"ם Rambam structures it. Whether prior there actually we're going to see
in the גמרא Gemara that there actually were more of the ברוך
אתהs baruch atah that were you know that were part of the
ברכת אבלים, birchat aveilim, more of a classic נוסח הברכה. nusach haberacha.
So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. You said it
was the מנין minyan eaten something? Presumably at the end yeah after
at the end of ברכת המזון birchat hamazon when you eat the
זית אבל. zeis avel.
What? No.
Where we if it's פנים חדשות panim chadashot you do it?
Throughout the whole week if there are פנים חדשות. panim chadashot. But
again whether the רמב"ם's Rambam version is exactly the גמרא's Gemara version,
we're going to see the גמרא Gemara has more of a classic
type of a ברוך אתה ה' baruch atah Hashem set of ברכות.
berachot. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. כי הא
דרבי חייא בר אבא Ki had d'Rav Chiya bar Abba like the
story of רבי חייא בר אבא, Rav Chiya bar Abba, מקרי בני
דריש לקיש הוי. mikrei b'nei deResh Lakish havai. He was the חדר
cheder teacher of ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish kids. He was taught them
מקרי בני mikrei b'nei he taught his kids. It says it's מקרא
*mikra* because it's תורה *Torah*, פסוקים psukim *psukim*,
and what happened, שכיב ליה ינוקא *shachiv lei yanuka*, and a child
of his died, this חדר cheder *cheder* teacher of ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish *Resh Lakish*'s kids. Oh, I'm sorry, some say מתני בריה דריש
לקיש *matnei breih de-Resh Lakish*, some say he taught a משנה mishna,
*mishnah* of ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Resh Lakish*'s sons. Okay, and שכיב
ליה ינוקא *shachiv lei yanuka*, so a child of this חדר *cheder*
teacher died of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. *Resh Lakish*'s kids' חדר *cheder*
teacher. יומא קמא לא אזל לגביה *yoma kama lo azal lagabei*, the
first day ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. *Resh Lakish* did not go to
pay a שבעה shiva *shiva* call. למחר
*lamachar*, the next day. So part of the point here being that
it was not the first day and still there was going to
be a ברכה bracha *bracha*. That's how this is a tie-in, right?
It's not the first day, it's the second day and ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish *Resh Lakish* is a פנים חדשות *panim chadashos*. It doesn't
tell us why he didn't go, maybe he was busy. Not like
he דוקא *davka* made a point of not going. It happens, sometimes
you don't pay a שבעה shivah *shiva* call on the first day.
He paid the second day, he was a פנים חדשות *panim chadashos*.
Okay, so there's the second day and he's a פנים חדשות *panim
chadashos*. So למחר דבריה ליהודה בר נחמני מתורגמניה
*lamachar davreih lehuda bar Nachmani meturgamaneih*. The second day he went and
he took יהודה בר נחמני Yehuda bar Nachmani *Yehuda bar Nachmani* who
was his מתורגמן meturgeman, *meturgaman*. מתורגמן meturgeman *meturgaman* is like somebody who
basically when he gave a שיעור *shiur* and he would say something
to him and then he would announce it to the
whole student, to all the students or to the whole community and
so on. So we're going to see how he is a sort
of loudspeaker but also he's given a little license sometimes to elaborate,
as we will see. So אמר ליה Amar lei: *amar lei*, so
then ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Resh Lakish* said to this יהודה Yehuda
בר נחמני *Yehuda bar Nachmani*, קום אימא מילתא כקבל ינוקא *kum eima
miltha kaveil yanuka*. Go, he said to him, and stand up and
say some words in honor, in commemoration of the child who passed
away. Okay, so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Resh Lakish* wasn't feeding him
the text, but he was acting on ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Resh
Lakish*'s behalf and saying some words for the sake of the
infant or the child. פתח ואמר patach ve'amar: *patach v'amar*, so he
stood up and he said the following פסוק pasuk? *pasuk*. פתח ואמר
patach ve'amar: *patach v'amar*, וירא ה' וינאץ מכעס בניו ובנתיו *vayar Hashem
vayina'atz mikas banav uvnotav*. Okay, God saw and he was angry from
the anger of his sons and daughters. דור שאבות מנאצים להקדוש ברוך
הוא *dor she'avot mena'atzim l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu*, a generation where the fathers
caused God to be like
angry, or
מנאצים *mena'atzim*, like נואץ *no'etz*, how does that translate, נואץ *no'etz*? I
don't know.
I'm trying to think of a good English word for נואץ *no'etz*.
מנאץ *mena'etz*.
Do you have it there? No? Provoke? Alright, fine. Okay, a דור
*dor*
that the fathers provoke להקדוש ברוך הוא *l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu*. כועס על
בניהם ועל בנותיהם ומתים כשהן קטנים *ko'eis al bneihem v'al bnoteihem umesim
kshehein ktanim*. So therefore, וירא ה' וינאץ *vayar Hashem vayina'atz*, so God
was provoked because and מכעס *mikas* the anger is directed at בניו
ובנתיו *banav uvnotav*, of course בניו ובנתיו *banav uvnotav* in the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* is God's children, but it means that the anger is
directed at the people's children and therefore their children die. So basically
he's saying your
kids die because
you did something to anger God.
Right, feel better. Right. איכא דאמרי *ika d'amrei*, maybe ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish *Resh Lakish* will learn from that not to leave the words
of נחמה nechama *nechama* to his מתורגמן meturgeman, *meturgaman*. ואיכא דאמרי *v'ika
d'amrei*, others say בחור היה
*bachur haya*, that he wasn't like a small child, he was a
young adult. והכי קאמר ליה *v'hachi ka'amar lei*, and so he quoted
a different פסוק *pasuk*. Here's the פסוק *pasuk* he said to him:
על כן על בחוריו לא ישמח ה' ואת יתומיו ואת אלמנותיו לא
ירחם *al kein al bachurav lo yismach Hashem v'et yetomav v'et almanotav
lo yerachem*. Therefore God will not rejoice over his young men, and
the orphans and widows he will not give compassion to. כי כלו
חנף ומרע *ki khulo chaneif umer'ah*, all of them are like blaspheming
and doing evil. וכל פה דבר נבלה *v'khol peh dover nevala*, and
all mouths speak abomination. בכל זאת לא שב אפו *bekhol zot lo
shav apo*, and even with this punishment God's anger is not turned
back, ועוד ידו נטויה yado netuya, *v'od yado netuya*, his hand is
still stretched out against the generation. מאי ועוד ידו נטויה yado netuya.
*mai v'od yado netuya*, what does it mean his hand is still
stretched against them? אמר רב חנא בר אבא *amar Rav Chana bar
Abba*, הכל יודעים כלה למה נכנסה לחופה *hakol yod'im kalla lama nichnesa
l'chuppa*. Everybody knows why the כלה *kalla* is going to go to
the חופה *chuppa*, very much tying into our מסכת masechet. *masechet*. אלא
ela, כל המנבל פיו ומוציא דבר נבלה מפיו *ella kol hamenabeil piv
umotzi davar nevala mipiv*, but anybody who makes his does ניבול פה
*nival peh*, right, that's a phrase that we have, and makes his
mouth abominable and says the thing explicitly, אפילו נחתם לו גזר דינו
של שבעים שנה לטובה *afilu nechtam lo gzar dino shel shiv'im shana
l'tova*, even if there was a for seventy good years it was
a decree for this person to live seventy good years, נהפך עליו
לרעה *nehepach alav l'ra'ah*, it reverses itself for evil. I don't know
exactly how we get that from the פסוק *pasuk* ועוד ידו נטויה
*v'od yado netuya*, like there seems to be, I'm not exactly, there
must be some play on words going on here that I don't
get exactly how it ties into that. In the end, it's about
נבלה מפיו *nevala mipiv* and וכל פה דבר נבלה *v'khol peh dover
nevala*. So anyway, which is also by the way fascinating because it
focuses on the woman, right? I mean, mostly often the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is much more concerned about the fact that men are always
having sexual thoughts. Doesn't tend to be focused on that or acknowledge
that so much for the women. Then here it says that everybody
knows why the כלה *kalla* is going to the חופה *chuppa*. Why
doesn't everybody know why the חתן *chosson*'s going to the חופה *chuppa*?
Right? Everybody's thinking, so again it's like very much from
the... I don't know, but I think it's fascinating that it's focused
on the fact that they're talking about the woman and not the
male. Anyway, so some play on words
either in יאוש or in דד, dad,
I don't know.
ידו נטויה, yeah, there's got to be some play on words going
on with ידו נטויה. I don't know if the Artscroll or Steinsaltz
suggest something, but there's got to be some way it's linking it
in. Anyway, so that was a little bit of a digression. That
wasn't exactly his point, the point of this מתורגמן, meturgeman. but it's
an interesting tie-in to our מסכת. Anyway, so בקיצור, bekitzur, he basically
said, yeah, this is a terrible thing that happened to him, must
be that you've done some terrible stuff. By the way, it's to
be acknowledged we can all say this, oh my god, this is
so absurd and whatever, but you know, people say pretty stupid things
at a שבעה shivah call. And there are definitely people that do
not, I mean, everybody, most people have really good intentions, but like
there's some people that ממש mamash don't know what to say and
they'll say stupid things that maybe don't get at the degree of
obviously wrong as this, but there definitely will be people that say
very, very painful and horrible things trying to, trying to be good,
with good intentions. Okay, so anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, אתא
לנחומי צעורי קא מצער ליה? ata lenichumei tzo'arei ka metza'er lei? So
the גמרא Gemara says, he was coming to give consolation and in
the end he's causing him this pain and anguish? So the גמרא
Gemara says, הכי קאמר ליה. hachi ka'amar lei. No, no, no, here's
how, what he meant to say: חשיב את לאתפוסי אדרא. chashiv at
le'atpusei adara.
You are so חשיב chashiv that you were punished for the sins
of the generation. So it wasn't just you, it's דור שמנאצין להקדוש
ברוך הוא, dor shemenatzin lehakadosh baruch hu, right? So
it's everybody's fault, and but you're so, you are of such a
high מדרגה madrega that you're the one that suffers for the generation.
So all right, so the point being that even if that was
what he was trying to say, that doesn't mean that it's the
right thing to say. So you know, it's again an excellent example
of somebody who thinks they're saying the right thing and,
I mean, look, a classic example is somebody who's suffering the loss
of a small child and it's like, oh, God doesn't give you
anything you can't bear, or, oh, I'm sure, you know, you'll have
other children, you'll move on, or whatever. People say these things and
they're completely terrible and they're devastating. So people don't know and they
say things that they think are well-intentioned. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara continues, although it would be nice if the גמרא Gemara was
a little more critical of even this תירוץ. teretz. Anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר ליה קום אימא מילתא כנגד שבחו
של הקדוש ברוך הוא. amar lei kum eima milta keneged shivcho shel
hakadosh baruch hu. It gets better now. Okay, so then ריש לקיש
said to him, now say things in praise of God, now that
you're done with that
נחמה nechamah, part.
What? Yeah, exactly. So the גמרא Gemara does not, does not make
it sound like ריש לקיש was displeased. The גמרא Gemara just voiced
its own critique of it.
פתח ואמר אל גדול ברוב גודלו אדיר וחזק ברוב נוראות מחיה מתים
במאמרו עושה גדולות עד אין חקר ונפלאות עד אין מספר ברוך אתה
ה' מחיה המתים.
patach ve'amar el gadol berov godlo adir vechazak berov nora'ot mechaye metim
bema'amaro ose gedolot ad ein
cheker venifla'ot ad ein mispar baruch ata Hashem mechaye hametim. Okay, so
here's a ברוך אתה ה' baruch ata Hashem ברכה bracha. and it's
מחיה המתים mechaye hametim in the context of a general praise of
God, but obviously highly relevant to a בית אבל. beit avel. אמר
ליה קום אימא מילתא כנגד אבילים. amar lei kum eima milta keneged
avelim.
Now say something in honor of the, you know, for the mourners.
This is not the standard ברכה.
bracha. What? What?
This is not the standard ברכה. bracha So the other, מחיה המתים,
mechaye hametim, that was in the context of praising God. Obviously all
of this is because of the mourners, but it's in the context
of saying it's praise of God. God does this.
Okay, fine. So the ברכת אבילים birkat avelim actually, well
we'll see, there's a series of ברכות. brachot. Let's see what all
the ברכות brachot are.
קום אימא מילתא כנגד אבילים.
kum eima milta keneged avelim. Now say something to the mourners and
we'll see how this is different than the other words, but the
other words were like why the kid died or something about the
kid, like, so here let's see, it's directly about the אבילים. avelim.
Let's see what it's
about. פתח ואמר אחינו המיוגעים המדוכאים באבל הזה
תנו לבבכם לחקור את
זאת זאת עומדת לעד נתיב הוא מששת ימי בראשית רבים שתו ורבים
ישתו כמשתה ראשונים כך משתה אחרונים. patach ve'amar acheinu hameyuga'im hameduka'im ba'avel
haze tnu levavkhem lachkor et zot zot omedet la'ad nativ hu misheshet
yimei bereshit rabim shatu verabim yishtu kemishte rishonim kakh mishte acharonim. כמשתה
ראשונים, kemishte rishonim, thank you, כמשתה אחרונים, kemishte acharonim, thank you. Like
the drinking of
the earliest, so the drinking of the later, you know, every, this
has happened in past generations, it'll happen in future. You're not alone
in this.
This is the way of the world.
אחינו בעל נחמות ינחם אתכם ברוך מנחם אבלים. acheinu ba'al nechamot yenachem
etkhem baruch menachem avelim. The master of consolations should console you. ברוך
מנחם אבלים, baruch menachem avelim, blessed is God who is מנחם אבלים.
menachem avelim. So it's words of trying
of consolation
like, this is a natural way of the world. So obviously when
bad things happen to you, you feel that God is against you
and they're all happening to you and you're being singled out. So
somehow acknowledging that this is a natural occurrence in the way of
all world maybe helps to put it. in some type of a
perspective and then ends with the fact that God, you should have
נחמה, nechamah. God should be מנחם menachem you. So that's very different
than the earlier thing which somehow spoke directly about the death of
the person, which did not, was not so successful in being a
נחמה.
So this would happen more often.
I mean it seems very poetic. I know. Well, no, but actual
that's presumably why his job as a מתורגמן meturgeman was in order
to come up with these types of things. But maybe he said
these things commonly, I don't know. Yes, these things to be very
much stylized ברכות brachot and things that presumably he would have said.
But did everybody say these ברכות? brachot? It doesn't sound that way.
It sounds like he was giving a little bit of latitude to
his מתורגמן, right? So it seems like we that as opposed to
when the גמרא Gemara said what is the ברכת חתנים birchat chatanim
and gave a fixed text, here it seems like the ברכת אבלים
birchat aveilim was allowed to be more flexible. Like maybe you were
supposed to end with, you know, have a series of ברכות, brachot,
one ended with מחיה מתים, mechayeh meitim, one ended with מנחם אבלים,
menachem aveilim, you know, but what you exactly said in the text
maybe was more flexible. So that would be a really interesting way
of balancing our experience of ניחום אבלים, nichum aveilim, right, with a
type of a liturgy and making it somewhat of a flexible or
shapable liturgy, which you know, with a certain structure associated with it.
So that's what it sort of seems we were dealing with. So
you have the, but the first one, which was just, was not
a ברוך אתה. Baruch Atah. That was about the person who had
died. But this is about ניחום אבלים. nichum aveilim.
Right, and also it just seems like, you know, they're just sitting
there and he was saying it. Right.
Oh, you mean the one, it wasn't, yeah, this is not clear
that it's connected to ברכת המזון. birchat hamazon. That is correct.
And it also doesn't say anything about there being, you know, a
מנין. minyan.
Yeah, but that might be because we said that already. But that's
true. The same way it was not, it was also not made
very central to the discussion of the ברכת חתנים birchat chatanim or
ברכת המזון. birchat hamazon. It was only sort of brought in at
the end.
Okay. יהודה Yehuda בר נחמני the מתורגמן. Exactly. Yep. And he's the
מתורגמן of רבי חייא בר אבא. Rabbi Chiya bar Abba. No, of
ריש לקיש. Ah, he's ריש לקיש.
The teacher has gone to, רבי חייא בר
אבא
Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba
was the, was the teacher whose son died. He was the אבל.
aveil. ריש לקיש is the מנחם. menachem. Okay. So
רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba was ריש לקיש's kids'
חדר teacher. That's why he went to pay a שבעה call. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: ברוך מנחם אבלים. Baruch Menachem
Aveilim. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: רבים שתו לימא, rabim shatu leima, רבים
ישתו לא לימא. rabim yishtu lo leima. You should say many have
drunk from its waters, don't say many will drink from its waters,
right? I mean it's not like it's not true, but why talk
about sort of like, you know, like the famous מדרש midrash by,
by you know, אהיה אשר אהיה, Eheyeh Asher Eheyeh, אהיה מם... Eheyeh
mam... it's like don't mention other צרות. tzarot. Like who needs to
mention things that haven't happened yet, that people will die in the
future, right? You don't want to suggest that other kids will die.
Well, that's maybe that's also true. משתה ראשונים לימא, mishteh rishonim leima,
משתה אחרונים לא לימא. mishteh acharonim lo leima. It was the earlier
drinkings you should say, not the later ones. דאמר רבי שמעון בן
לקיש, D'amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, וכן תני משמיה דרבי יוסי. vechen
tani mishmei de'Rabbi Yosi. So interestingly, ריש לקיש himself said, לעולם אל
יפתח אדם פיו לשטן. le'olam al yiftach adam piv l'Satan. You should
not open up your mouth to the Satan, right? Don't mention, you
know, the possibility of something bad, you're just asking for it to
happen. אמר רב יוסף: Amar Rav Yosef: מאי קרא? mai kra? What's
the פסוק? כסדום היינו לעמורה דמינו. k'Sdom hayinu l'Amora daminu. We were
like Sodom and Amora. מאי אהדר ליה? Mai ahadar lei? and what's
the next verse? שמעו דבר השם קציני סדום. shim'u devar Hashem ktzinei
Sdom. That they're being, that they're being called the sort of rulers
of Sodom. They're being made, made like exactly what they were afraid
of. אמר ליה: Amar lei: קום אימא מילתא כנגד מנחמי אבלים. kum
eima milta keneged menachmei aveilim. Now say a ברכה bracha for the
מנחמים, menachamim, for the people that have all come to to pay
a שבעה call. So פתח ואמר: אחינו גומלי חסדים בני גומלי חסדים.
acheinu gomlei chasadim bnei gomlei chasadim. Our brethren who give, you know,
acts of חסד, chesed, the children of those who who do acts
of חסד. chesed. המחזיקים בבריתו של אברהם אבינו. hamachazikim bivrito shel Avraham
Avinu. Follow in the path of אברהם Avraham who does acts of
חסד. chesed. There's a פסוק here כי ידעתיו למען אשר יצוה, ki
yedativ l'ma'an asher yetzaveh, right, ושמרו דרך השם לעשות צדקה ומשפט. veshamru
derech Hashem la'asot tzedakah u'mishpat. But for, but first of all, it
doesn't sound here like we're quoting פסוקים in these ברכות. brachot. And
number two, צדקה ומשפט tzedakah u'mishpat is not exactly the model we're
talking about right now. There's other examples of אברהם Avraham being a
גומל חסד gomel chesed like you know, the whole הכנסת אורחים hachnasat
orchim and other types of things. Anyway, אחינו בעל הגמול ישלם לכם
גמולכם. acheinu ba'al hagemul yeshalem lachem gmulchem. Our
brethren, the, the master of kindness of good deeds, God will pay
for you for your kind deeds. ברוך אתה השם משלם הגמול. Baruch
Atah Hashem meshalem hagemul. Blessed are You God who pays I know,
it didn't say before, oh yeah, before it did have the השם.
Hashem. I don't know, you have to look at the different נוסחאות.
nuschaot. Okay, God will, will pay you back for your acts of
kindness. אמר ליה: קום אימא מילתא כנגד כל ישראל. kum eima milta
keneged kol Yisrael. Say a ברכה relating to all of the Jewish
people. פתח ואמר: Okay, ריבונו העולמים, Ribono ha'olamim, פדה והצל. pedeh ve'hatzel.
God, Master of the universe, redeem and save, מלט והושע עמך ישראל.
malet ve'hosha amcha Yisrael. Your nation Israel, מן הדבר ומן החרב ומן
הביזה. min hadever u'min hacherev u'min habizah. From pestilence and sword and
from booty, from from whatever. ומן השידפון ומן הירקון, u'min hashidafon u'min
hayarkon, you know, from famine and whatever, right, blight, blout, blight, blight,
and מכל מיני פורענויות המתרגשות ובאות לעולם. mkol minei puranuyot hamitragshot u'va'ot
l'olam. From all that things that can come to the world. טרם
נקרא ואתה תענה. terem nikra ve'atah ta'aneh. Even before we call out
You should answer. ברוך אתה Baruch Atah or or or question again
also doesn't say the השם Hashem explicitly here, ברוך אתה עוצר המגפה.
Baruch Atah otzer hamagefah. Blessed are You God who holds back the
you know a plague, which basically also means that this should not
be a סימן רע siman ra of bad things to come to
the people. So you're making this blessing that God will protect us
from all that things, right, when you know and so on. So
that's what it sort of seems we were dealing with. So you
had the... Was it always these were like a series of ברכות
brachot that ended with these specific סיומים siumim and he just filled
in the themes? Did ריש לקיש decide which סיומים siumim and somebody
else might have said, you know, a different? I mean but it
sounds like there was at least whether it could existed prior to
ריש לקיש or after, it seems like there was a type of
a defined structure, right, for the person who had died, for the
אבל, avel, for the מנחמים, menachamim, for God מחיה מתים mechaye meitim
and for like the future and for כלל ישראל. Klall Yisrael. All
right and presumably people were able to fill in the blanks.
Okay. אמר עולא ואמרי לה במתניתא תנו. Amar Ulla v'amri la b'matnita
tanu. עולא Ulla said and some say we taught in a
ברייתא. Braita. עשרה כוסות תקנו חכמים בבית האבל. Asara cosot tiknu chachamim
b'veit ha'avel. They made ten cups of wine that you would drink
in the ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon in the בית האבל. beit ha'avel.
I'm not... not in all the ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, excuse me,
ten in total. שלושה קודם אכילה, Sheloshah kodem achilah, three before you
begin eating, כדי לשתוח את פני מעיו kidei listoch et p'nei me'av
in order to aid in your appetite. שלושה בתוך האכילה, Sheloshah b'toch
ha'achilah, three during the eating, כדי לשרות אכילה kidei lishrot achilah in
order to sort of settle the food, שבפני מעיו, she'b'pnei me'av, וארבעה
לאחר אכילה v'arba'ah l'achar achilah and four after the eating. אחד כנגד
הזן, Echad k'neged hazan, one what you would say for the ברכת
birkat of הזן את הכל, hazan et hakol, אחד כנגד ברכת הארץ
echad k'neged birkat ha'aretz על הארץ ועל המזון, al ha'aretz v'al hamazon,
ואחד כנגד בונה ירושלים, v'echad k'neged boneh Yerushalayim, ואחד כנגד הטוב והמטיב.
v'echad k'neged hatov v'hameitiv. So you've got ten. Presumably it was a
lot also because it was a helpful way of, well, I don't
know if now we would say it's helpful, but it was a
way that was being used to help right, drown your sorrows and
deal with your grief. ישתו ישנים. Ishtu yeshanim. Yeah, exactly. Thank you,
right. Thank you very much. Right, the whole idea of that many
have drunk from these waters and it's a משתה mishte and a
משתה mishte is often used as like a drinking party or certainly
wine, משתה חתנים, mishte chatanim, right, probably very much so context to
the amount of wine that they would have בבית האבל. b'veit ha'avel.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. הוסיפו עליהן, Hosifu aleihen,
then they added to them, maybe because people still needed to drink
more wine or drinking more wine, so they maybe wanted to give
it some more significance. הוסיפו עליהן ארבע, Hosifu aleihen arba, four more.
אחד כנגד חזני העיר Echad k'neged chazanei ha'ir ואחד כנגד פרנסי העיר
v'echad k'neged parnasei ha'ir ואחד
כנגד בית המקדש v'echad k'neged beit hamikdash ואחד כנגד רבן גמליאל.
v'echad k'neged
Rabban Gamliel. So, two for the חזנים chazanim and the פרנסים, parnasim,
presumably because the community here is like taking care, you know, of
the אבלים avelim and there's that sense of communal support. The one
of כנגד בית המקדש k'neged beit hamikdash is presumably like looking towards
a future time when there will be no, you know, no sorrow.
ורבן גמליאל v'Rabban Gamliel is as like the נשיא. Nasi. So again,
I'm somehow just in honor of him presumably. התחילו. Hitchilu. Again, I'm
not sure if this is רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel of יבנה Yavne
or רבן גמליאל הזקן. Rabban Gamliel Hazaken. If it's רבן גמליאל הזקן,
Rabban Gamliel Hazaken, then there was a present בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash
that it actually was. No, רש"י Rashi says that it was after
the חורבן. churban. תקנו ברכת הניחומים שינחמנו המקום בבנינו מאבלנו שאנו מתאבלים
עליו כעל מת.
Tiknu birkat hanichumim sheyenachamenu hamakom b'vinyano me'avelenu she'anu mitabelim
alav k'al met.
Ah. רש"י Rashi says better than I was saying. No חידוש chiddush
there. That
it's not just the time of a messianic looking, but, you know,
but a type of a communal אבלות. avelut. We're all אבלים avelim
on the חורבן הבית. Churban Habayit. So God should also console us
for our אבלות avelut and בניין הבית. binyan habayit. Okay. התחילו היו
שותין ומשתכרין, Hitchilu hayu shotin umishtakrin, but then they were drinking way
too much and getting drunk. Because ten was... ten was, right, but
fourteen already is a little over. Okay. החזירו דבר ליושנו. Hechziru davar
l'yoshno. It reversed, they reverted it back to the old way, ten.
Okay. מאי רבן גמליאל, Mai Rabban Gamliel, why for רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel did they specifically have a drink? דתניא, D'tanya, בראשונה היו הוצאת
המת קשה לקרוביו יותר ממיתתו. barishona hayu hotza'at hamet kashah likrovav yoter
mimitato. The actual burial of the... of the מת met was worse
to the... to the קרוביו krovav than the actual... than the death
itself, than the grieving over the death. Why? Because it was so
expensive. It created such a tremendous burden. עד שהיו מניחין אותו ובורחין,
Ad she'hayu menichim oto v'borchin, and they would basically abandon their dead,
right, because they couldn't because, you know, afford the expense of burial.
עד שבא רבן גמליאל ונהג קלות
בעצמו והוציאו בכלי פשתן.
Ad sheba Rabban Gamliel v'nahag
kalut b'atzmo v'hotzi'u bichli pishtan.
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel commanded that when he died, they would have
a very, very simple funeral, just simple linen garments. ונהגו כל העם
אחריו להוציא בכלי פשתן
V'nahagu kol ha'am acharav l'hotzi
bichli pishtan and
therefore that set the standard and afterwards
everybody had simple funerals and therefore in memory of רבן גמליאל, Rabban
Gamliel, so he wasn't the living נשיא, Nasi, it was in memory
of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and what he had done for the
sake of the
אבלים, avelim, they
drank
a special cup of wine in his honor. אמר פפא והאידנא נהגא
אפילו בצרדא בר זוזא. Amar Papa v'idna nahaga afilu b'tzarda bar zuza.
Nowadays people have even a simple canvas sack, you know, worth just
a dollar. We do it very, very simple and unadorned. And by
the way, you know, very important in terms of like Hebrew Free
Burial Society, in terms of thinking about the, you know, that sense
of the commitment to make sure that no matter how poor like
every, you know, every Jew is afforded a, you know, a funeral
and a burial. But so this obviously is not a, you know,
this is an old problem which still is sometimes very challenging for
people, but thank God there are, you know, institutions that really help
to ensure that people will be buried, yes. And רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel was a very wealthy man. And רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel right,
he was the נשיא. Nasi. So him insisting on only תכריכין tachrichin
was a message. Exactly. That's exactly, yes. I should have pointed that
out. Yes, obviously he was extremely wealthy, he was the most important
person of the time, and he had the most simplest funeral, yes.
So it sounds, based on seeing עשרה כוסות תקנו חכמים בבית האבל,
Asara cosot tiknu chachamim b'veit ha'avel, so like you know, what happened
to that? Is it like you know... I know. Yeah, I know.
And what happened to the ברכת אבלים Birkat Avelim and where'd it
all go? I don't know, but... Anyway, but here we do see,
you know, but yes, and also exactly what degree is this tied
into the ברכת המזון birchas hamazon or not, you know, it was
a similar ambiguity by the שבע ברכות sheva brachos although context clarified
that a little bit more by the שבע ברכות. sheva brachos. Now
we move on. So all of that, actually the דפים dappim had
a nice theme broken up by the דף. daf. Of course, to
us it's a little bit of a mixed theme because we were
behind. So anyway, so that was yesterday's דף. daf. That was all
about, you know, it's very it's very nice how it worked out
sort of like almost like, you know, you know like graphically, not
graphically but you know like physically, like עמוד א' amud aleph was
ברכות חתנים birchos chasanim and עמוד ב' amud bais was ברכות אבלים.
birchos aveilim. And that whole דף daf was about the special ברכות
brachos around weddings and funerals. Now we get to a much more
technical legal discussion around, not technical, right, right exactly, weddings, funerals, anyway
we get to a much more technical legal discussion around that first
night and about why we're making him, them, why they're doing it
right before the בית דין beis din meets the next morning because
he might discover she's not a virgin and what are the implications
of all of that? So we really are going to have an,
and that is going to be the whole theme of this דף.
daf. So each דף daf really is a very distinct theme to
it. Yes. It's true, in other words, in other words, I mean
we practice that, to us you drink wine at the סעודת הבראה
seudas havra'ah for sure, right? In other words at the, but even
the example is, well the סעודת, I don't know, but the סעודת
הבראה is a very simple סעודה. seuda. But no, I mean they
actually say that an אונן onen doesn't drink wine, but they allowed
an אבל avel to drink wine as a way of dealing with
his grief. So today what's our practice? Yeah, we don't דווקא davka
make a point. Yeah, Michael said that too. We don't make a
point, I mean not only do we not have this תקנה takana
of all of these כוסות cosos like it's not like we even
think it's an idea of drinking wine, you know. All right, okay,
I know. אמר רבי אלעזר. Amar Rabbi Elazar. Now, new theme. Okay,
the guy comes up the comes the next morning and says she
wasn't a virgin. What are the implications? Okay, now there's two ways
that he could say that she's not a virgin. One is he
could say there was no blood. Okay, and remember we mentioned earlier
and we'll discuss later that they had like all of these like
guards at the door and these special sheets or whatever that they
were going to see if there was blood or not. So if
there's no blood, so there actually, there's a case where there presumably
is like evidence to see or lack of evidence to see. Of
course he could have said we never had sex, that's why there's
no blood, or he could have said other things. But anyway at
least there's something more concrete to either see whether it happened or
didn't, even though there might be a dispute about whether they actually,
you know, actually had intercourse or not, but or whether the you
know the blood was lost or or who knows you know was
on the sheet and it was and it was lost or whatever.
But anyway you're dealing with the possibility of some some concrete evidence
or lack of evidence. The other possibility is not the issue of
blood, but he actually says in the act of sex itself, I
could tell that she was no longer a virgin, that basically it
was like it was not it was unobstructed. You know there was
no hymen there, I can just tell experientially. And that's what the
גמרא Gemara calls the טענת פתח פתוח, tainas pesach pasuach, the door
was already open. All right, again going to that imagery, you know,
about the house and so on that we discussed before. Okay, so
the question is going to be saying that there was no blood
is something that he could see, and that clearly, whether, you know,
he's, whether he's going to be believed to hurt her? No, because
there's no actual evidence. But at least to hurt himself or maybe
in monetary matters, certainly not as a basis to make her forbidden
on him. Because, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, excuse me, I got ahead
of myself. When he says there's no blood, then there is right,
then then we okay I've got ahead of myself. So the claim
of, so so there's two questions here, Tzvi. One question is whether
we think he actually really knows what he's talking about, right? Like
even in terms of his own mindset, not whether it's objectively true.
If there's no witnesses we don't know it's objectively true. At the
end of the day all we have to go on is his
say-so. But even within the context of his say-so, do we think
that he actually knows what he's talking about or he he even
in his own mind is making a mistake, right? You see the
difference?
Like, it could still be a virgin, you didn't do it right,
let's take it this point. Nobody, his say-so is never going to
get her killed for an act of adultery, right? Because it's only
his say-so. There's no witnesses. But it might have the effect of
saying if you say she's not a virgin and you say maybe
let's say she committed adultery, well you're not allowed to continue living
with her. We're not saying she did it or not. We don't
know. There are no witnesses. But based on your own say-so you
shouldn't be allowed to continue to live with her. Okay, so that's
like you are bound by your own say-so even though it's not
objectively true. And the issue of פתח פתוח pesach pasuach is the
issue if he says I know she's not a virgin and she
committed adultery or whatever because because there was no blood, fine, you
can't prove it. It's only your own say-so, but you're bound by
it. But if he says I know because I did not the
you know the this act of intercourse was unobstructed and I could
tell there was no hymen, maybe maybe you don't even know what
you're talking about. You know, even in your own mind that's what
you think happened but maybe you know maybe maybe you have nothing,
you don't really have enough experience and you don't have enough instance
to actually even come to that conclusion even in which within the
context of even assuming you are telling the truth or you think
you're telling the truth. So that's the question of פתח פתוח. pesach
pasuach. Is he טועה? toeh? Okay, objectively
whenever... אמר רב אלעזר *Amar Rav Elazar*, האומר פתח פתוח מצאתי
petach patuach
matzati *HaOmer Petach Patuach Matzasi*. A man says, I found the door
already open, so נאמן לאוסרה עליו le'osrah alav. *neeman l'osrah alav*, makes
her forbidden to him. Meaning, that's the principle of שויה אנפשיה חתיכה
דאיסורא shavya anafshei chaticha d'issura *shavye anafshei chaticha d'issura*, that if you
say something is forbidden to you then it is, because you know
you claim this is the reality. This piece of meat you say
is חזיר chazir *chazir*, even if it's not, you're bound by that.
That's an idea that like you have to be true to at
least your own claim of what the facts are. Okay, so it's
but it doesn't mean that it's objectively true, just means you're bound
by it. Now of course she's the one that's going to have
to suffer because then we're going to demand that he give her
a divorce and so on, but at least he'll pay the כתובה
ksuba, *kesubah* etc., etc. Okay, but he is forbidden because he claims
that she's forbidden to him because he claims essentially she's committed adultery.
And a woman who commits adultery, what?
תהא מותרת *teha muteres*?
Oh, we'll talk about alright we'll get to all that. A woman
who commits adultery is forbidden to her husband. So based on your
own claim she's forbidden to you. You are bound by your own
claim. Okay. Now that so there's two assumptions here. Number one is
שויה shavya אנפשיה חתיכה דאיסורא *shavye anafshei chaticha d'issura*, you're bound by
your own claim, but the other is the חידוש chiddush? *chiddush* that
it applies even by פתח פתוח petach patuach *petach patuach* where you
might not exactly even know what you're talking about, even in your
own mind. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. So before
we're going to get to the פתח פתוח petach patuach *petach patuach*
part in a minute, but first let's look at the idea about
what the implications of your claim is. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says ואימא ספק ספיקא safek sefeika. הוא *ve'eima sfeik sfeika hu*. Why
is that? Thank you. ספק ספיקא safek sefeika הוא *sfeik sfeika hu*,
it's a double ספק safek. *safek*. Even according to your claim, even
within the context of your claim, it's not clear she committed adultery.
All you know is that she wasn't a virgin. So here's the
double doubt. ספק safek תחתיו ספק safek אין תחתיו *safek tachtav safek
ein tachtav*. Maybe she had sex after the קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin* and
literally under you, after the קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin*. Right, this is the
נישואין nisu'in, *nisuin*, but she was married for the last I don't
know five years. So maybe she had sex since the קידושין *kiddushin*
and then she would have committed adultery and then she would be
forbidden to you. ספק אין תחתיו *safek ein tachtav*, or maybe it
was before the act of קידושין *kiddushin* and then she's not a
virgin but she didn't commit adultery. So that's one ספק *safek*. ואם
תמצא לומר תחתיו *v'im timtza lomar tachtav*, and if you say that
it was after you after after קידושין *kiddushin*, ספק באונס ספק ברצון
*safek b'ones safek b'ratzon*. Maybe she had maybe she was forced to
have sex, maybe it was a rape, and then she also wouldn't
be forbidden to you. Or maybe it was willing. So there's a
double ספק *safek*. It both has to have been after the act
of קידושין *kiddushin* and willingly, and therefore even if what you are
saying is true, even within the context that
is you know ignore the fact whether we have objective evidence, but
even if it's true that she wasn't a virgin, she's not necessarily
that doesn't make her forbidden to you because it's a double doubt
whether that would mean that she had committed adultery.
Is it a
triple ספק *safek* in any of this? It might, but we're not-
no, not in terms of his own making her forbidden to him
because it's not about an objective question.
No, because he says שויה shavya אנפשיה *shavye
anafshei* yeah because I- no, that wouldn't matter. It's all because and
about the implications of his claim.
Okay, so- but it's a triple ספק *safek* if he might not
know what he's talking about?
We're going to get to that. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says לא צריכא *lo tzricha*. No, you need it for a case
of באשת כהן *b'eishess kohen*, the wife of a כהן *kohen*. The
wife of a כהן *kohen* it wouldn't matter if she was raped,
she would still be forbidden to him. ואיבעית אימא באשת ישראל כגון
דקיבל בה אביה קידושין פחותה מבת שלש שנים ויום אחד *v'iba'is eima
b'eishess Yisrael k'gon d'kibel bah aviha kiddushin pchusah mibas shalosh shanim v'yom
echad*. Or it could be that she's married to a ישראל *Yisrael*
but the father married her off under three years old. So why
does that matter? Because if he married her off under three years
old then she couldn't have had sex before the קידושין *kiddushin*. I
mean she could have had sex before the קידושין *kiddushin* but the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that ביאה *biah* after under the age of
three the hymen will grow back. So therefore if she doesn't have
a hymen it only would be because she had sex after three.
And if it's because she had sex after three then she was
already married and therefore there's only one question: ספק באונס ספק ברצון
*safek b'ones safek b'ratzon*. Now תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* asks another question. תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot* says but why isn't it a possibility that she had
sex willingly but she was under the age of twelve and that's
basically statutory rape, פיתוי קטנה אונס *pituy ketanah ones*. And even if
she agreed to it under the age of twelve it you know
would be it would be considered an אונס *ones* and therefore and
therefore it would not make her forbidden to him. So it still
is a double doubt. Maybe it was a rape, maybe it was
willing, and even if it was willing, maybe it was willing when
she was a minor and therefore it also doesn't make her forbidden.
So תוספות *Tosafot* says no because that case basically collapses into a
case of אונס *ones*. Since we say that you know being willing
under you know as a minor is considered rape, statutory rape is
considered אונס *ones*, so then it boils down to one ספק *safek*.
Maybe it was אונס *ones*, maybe it was not אונס *ones*. There're
two types of אונס *ones*. An אונס *ones* because you physically the
guy forced himself on her and an אונס *ones* because her דעת
*da'at* wasn't sufficient because she was a minor. Okay. And that's an
important principle in ספק ספיקא *sfeik sfeika*. That if basically some of
the questions all collapse into the same question it doesn't help create
a ספק ספיקא *sfeik sfeika*. They have to be different types of
questions. Alright, so the two types of questions are before after קידושין
*kiddushin* and whether it was willing or rape. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says we can reduce it to one ספק *safek* if basically
either rape doesn't matter because it's a wife of a כהן *kohen*
or there wasn't a possibility before קידושין *kiddushin* because she was married
off under three years old. Okay. So that's the principle so therefore
we got this idea that if there's based on his
claim... Were his claim true that she wasn't a virgin, if we
had evidence to the fact, we would say she's forbidden, because then
it's one ספק that she had committed adultery and therefore we would
say she's forbidden. So therefore, even though we don't have objective evidence
to that because he claims it, he is bound by that even
though, again, it's going to impact her as well. So now the
גמרא Gemara says מאי קמשמע לן, mai kamashma lan, so what is
this teaching us? תנינא, tenina, we taught this already, or a משנה,
Mishna I think. האומר לאשה
קדשתיך והיא אומרת לא קדשתני. haomer l'isha kidashticha v'hi omeret lo kidashtani.
A man says to a woman, I married you, and she says
you didn't marry me, and there's no
witnesses. He says he did it in front of witnesses, but there's
no witness because otherwise it wouldn't be a קידושין, but there's no
witnesses to make this claim. היא מותרת בקרוביו. hi muteret bikrovav. She
says she's not married, so, and there's no objective evidence she's married,
so she can marry his relatives. She can marry his brother, his
father, whatever, because she claims she's not married to him and there's
no objective evidence. Go ahead. והוא, v'hu, but because he said that
he was married to her, he is bound by his own claim.
הוא אסור בקרובותיה. hu assur bikrovoteha. He's forbidden with her relatives because
he's claiming he is married to her. Okay, so you see you
have this idea of שויה shavya that when there's a debate of
husband and wife about something or whatever, a man and woman or
whatever and so on, the person is at least, and there's no
objective evidence, the person is at least bound by their own claim.
So what's the חידוש? chiddush So the גמרא Gemara says מהו דתימא
התם דודאי קים ליה. mahu detema hatam davka kim lei. There he
knows whether he married her. So he said, right? So therefore, of
course
he's going to be bound by his own claim. אבל הכא מקרא
ולא קים ליה. aval hacha mikra v'lo kim lei.
I would say he doesn't know what he's talking about. Yes, in
your mind you think that she wasn't a virgin, but you have
no way of knowing. So therefore, you don't even say קים ליה
kim lei here, right? It was just a stupid conclusion that you
drew. Even in your own mind, you know, even if what you
were saying was true, that you experienced that, you know, that's no
proof that it actually is the case that she wasn't a virgin.
No, no, he just said, through the act of sex it felt
to me like she already
was no longer a virgin. So קמשמע לן kamashma lan that we
don't say that, that we say that his claim that פתח פתוח
petach patuach is enough of a claim that, again, he's bound by
it. Okay, it's not considered, we don't assume he's making a mistake
and he doesn't know what he's talking about. Alright, now the other
חידוש chiddush you could say is that this principle of שויה maybe
doesn't work together with the ספק. שויה is if I say this
is a piece of חזיר in front of me, or as I
say I married this woman, I'm forbidden to her relatives. Let's say
I say this is a piece of ספק חזיר safek chazir in
front of me. Ah! A piece of ספק חזיר, safek chazir, ספק
דאורייתא לחומרא, safek d'oraita l'chumra, you can't eat it. Everybody else can
eat it because there's no evidence, but you can't because you said
it's ספק חזיר. safek chazir. Is that clear? So that's already, that's
another חידוש chiddush that the גמרא Gemara didn't point out. Not only
might he be making a mistake, but even if it's true that
she wasn't a virgin, he's not saying she's definitely forbidden, right? So
that we're adding that to the idea of שויה אנפשיה חתיכה דאיסורא
that he makes a claim, he's bound by its consequences even if
that consequence only is because of doubtful sort of situations, not a
definite type of a reality that he's claiming to, and that the
claim of פתח פתוח petach patuach is a sufficient—we don't say he
doesn't know what he's talking about. Okay, so those two things. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. ומי אמר רבי אלעזר הכי, umi amar rabbi elazar hachi, did
Rabbi Elazar really say that? דאמר רבי אלעזר אין אשה נעשית על
בעלה אלא על עסקי קינוי וסתירה וכמעשה שהיה. d'amar rabbi elazar ein
isha ne'eset al ba'ala ela al iskei kinu v'stira u'kema'aseh shehaya. A
woman is only forbidden on her husband if you have like the
story of a סוטה, sota, like she was, you know, that the
husband warned her not to be with another man and then she
went into private, and just like that story. What story? So it's
the story of David and Batsheva. Of course the גמרא's Gemara going
to say David and Batsheva was not—nobody was warning the woman and
Uriah didn't warn her, I don't want to see you with דוד
המלך. David HaMelech. So the גמרא Gemara will get to that in
a minute. But anyway, the point right now is a woman's only
forbidden on her husband in the סוטה sota process, not just based
on his own
claim. So the גמרא Gemara says, first the גמרא Gemara addresses this
מעשה שהיה. ma'aseh shehaya. ותסברא, v'tisbara, does anyway that statement make sense?
מעשה שהיה בקינוי וסתירה הוה ליה? ma'aseh shehaya b'kinu v'stira hava lei?
Was the story with David and Batsheva with a warning and going
into hiding after the warning, private? ועוד מי אסורה, v'od mi assura,
and number two, since when was Batsheva אסורה assura to David? Right,
she kept her after he got Uriah killed, he kept her, so
obviously for some reason he avoided the consequences that a woman who
commits adultery is forbidden to her husband and to the man she
committed adultery with, and we're going to have to figure that out.
But anyway, why are you bringing in the whole story of David?
That's completely irrelevant, the facts are different and the law was different
there. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא, no, על עסקי קינוי וסתירה,
al iskei kinu v'stira, here's how you have to read it, I'm
sorry, הלא קשיא הכי קאמר אין אשה נעשית על בעלה אלא על
עסקי קינוי וסתירה ממעשה שהיה. haloka kashya hachi ka'amar ein isha ne'eset
al ba'ala ela al iskei kinu v'stira mimma'aseh shehaya. You can learn
out that a woman is only forbidden through a סוטה sota process
from the story of David and Batsheva. How do you learn it
out from there? דלא הוה קינוי וסתירה ולא איתסרא. delo hava kinu
v'stira v'lo itasra. Because since there wasn't there the סוטה sota process,
that's why she wasn't forbidden to David. So from the fact that
she wasn't forbidden to David, you can learn out the only way
a woman is forbidden is through a סוטה sota process. Of course
it's a little absurd because she definitely had committed adultery. סוטה's sota
only if you don't know, right? So still, the question still remains
open, how could David continue to have lived with her if she
definitely— committed adultery. So we'll worry about that in a minute. Let's
not worry about that right now. מכל מקום קשיא קינא ונסתרה אם
פתח פתוח לו. Mikol makom kasha kina v'nistira im petach patuach lo.
Nevertheless, you've got this problem. You see that it's only through the
קינוי וסתירה kinui v'stira process a woman is forbidden, not just through
some person's claim that she wasn't a virgin. So the גמרא Gemara.
says one minute. ולטעמיך קינוי וסתירה אין עדים לא? U'letaymeich kinui v'stira
in edim lo? One minute. According to you, do you really think
it means that the only way a woman is forbidden to her
husband is with the סוטה Sotah process? What if there's witnesses she
committed adultery? Of course she'd be forbidden to her husband. So we
don't need to exclude all other things. Now of course that's not
a good question because what he might have meant to say is
without objective evidence, the only way she's forbidden is the סוטה Sotah
process because the סוטה Sotah you have a high degree of suspicion,
right? And even suspicion isn't enough until you do the formal סוטה
Sotah process, right? Everybody understand that, right? That's the חידוש chiddush, of
סוטה. Sotah. You don't actually know, but you have because you went
through this whole formal process that and and plus this high degree
of likelihood, that combines to make her forbidden. So the statement obviously
isn't excluding עדים. edim. What it's saying is less than עדים, edim,
this is the only way. So certainly it does still seem to
argue that a person's claim out in a vacuum should not be
enough. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with it. אלא
הכי קאמר: Ela hachi ka'amar: איש שנסתרה באחד Ish she'nistra b'echad having
less than two עדים edim like one עד, ed, a woman isn't
forbidden to her husband, אלא בשני עדים. ela b'shnei edim. You need
two עדים. edim. וקינוי וסתירה אפילו בעד אחד נמי. V'kinui v'stira afilu
b'ed echad nami. But if you do the סוטה Sotah process even
one עד ed will be sufficient. ופתח פתוח כשני עדים דמי. U'petach
patuach k'shnei edim dami. Oh, and did we by the way forget
to mention that if he makes the claim that counts like two
עדים? edim? Why? Because a person is believed against themselves like a
hundred עדים. edim. נאמן אדם על עצמו כמאה עדים. Ne'eman adam al
atzmo k'mea edim. You know, so of course this is the question
was much better than the answer. The question basically is we have
a statement that says anything less than two עדים edim or the
סוטה Sotah process, a woman won't be forbidden to her husband. And
then we say, oh, did I forget to mention that if the
guy just makes the claim out of the blue, then then that's
also counts like two עדים edim and
she also is forbidden on you? Right?
I mean you understand the irony of this, right? A woman isn't
forbidden except with a סוטה. Sotah. Oh, but if you say she
committed adultery, if you're the husband and you say she committed adultery,
then she also is forbidden on you, right? So the question is
obviously much better than the answer. All right, but anyway the גמרא
Gemara is sticking to its but they're both statements of רבי אלעזר,
Rabbi Elazar, so we have to reconcile.
And פתח פתוח מצאתי pesach patuach m'tsasi? equals she committed adultery in
this way.
Well, it creates a it puts a fact on the table that
in certain circumstances allows us to make a ספק that she committed
adultery. And that's also the חידוש, Chiddush right? That even when you
say that שוויא אנפשיה חתיכה דאיסורא shavya anafshei chaticha d'issura and you're
bound by your own statement, that might be when your statement directly
states that this thing is forbidden. Here, besides the fact that you
in your own mind might be making a mistake, you're only saying
a fact: she wasn't a virgin. Oh, you say she's not a
virgin, that means she's a ספק committed adultery, therefore she is forbidden
on you. So there's like a lot of חידושים chiddushim to say
that it will have this type of a consequence. The other type
of thing that we should mention is רש"י Rashi and תוספות both
ask, well, I don't get it. Why isn't he just saying that
there was no blood? Why are we going to the פתח פתוח
pesach patuach which is not as
as concrete? And we say he might be making a mistake, presumably
he couldn't say פתח פתוח pesach patuach if there was blood. So
presumably there's no blood. So why isn't he just saying there's no
blood?
Right, so take a look at the top רש"י Rashi of the
page. Okay, האומר פתח פתוח מצאתי וטענת דמים אין לו, Ha'omer petach
patuach matzati v'ta'anat damim ein lo, כגון שמשפחת דורקנוס שאין להם דם
בבתוליהן. kegon she'mishpachat Dorkenos she'ein lahem dam b'betulihen.
Maybe she's from a certain family that doesn't have really a they
don't bleed by they have a very thin hymen or something. או
שנאבדה ממנו מפה ולא ידע אם היה דם.
O she'ne'evda mimenu mapa v'lo yada
im haya dam.
Or that the actual sheet was lost, so that we can't be
talking about. So we're going to talk about this. Okay, and by
the way, the תוספות gets into a whole other discussion about what
if she's actually not a young woman? What if she's a בוגרת?
bogeret? What if she's like she's not twelve, she's all of fifteen
or seventeen, maybe that maybe a woman like that won't have as
much blood when she when the hymen breaks? Or what if she's
a מוכת עץ? mukat etz? Questions Michael asked. So there's all these
other questions. But one thing you have to see is for some
reason he can't make the claim of no blood, he's making this
claim. And there's two חידושים chiddushim here. חידוש chidush? number one is
that we assume that he knows what he's talking about, at least
in his own mind. I mean, we're not assuming it's objectively true,
but within his claim, he knows what he's talking about. And number
two, even though he's not saying she's definitely forbidden to him, we
add that and we say, well, if we did have this fact,
then we'd say שספק she'safek committed adultery, therefore she is forbidden. But
again, that would only mean in the case of אשת כהן eshet
kohen or פחות מבת ג' pachot mibat gimmel because otherwise it's a
ספק ספיקא. Yes. Even on modern think we're not able to incriminate
ourselves. Is that correct? Well, you I mean, you can waive your
your Fifth Amendment right,
but actually more in הלכה halacha you're not able to incriminate yourself
so there's no way you can waive that in הלכה. halacha.
But you're not incriminating yourself. You are restricting yourself. Right? I thought
you said that she a person is believed against against
himself like a hundred. Yeah, no, but that's self-incrimination.
No. Believed against yourself only in monetary matters, like if you say
I owe somebody a thousand dollars, you're believed, not in criminal matters,
not in things that are not monetary. And in matters like this
which is about saying things are forbidden to you. No, let’s move
on. Okay, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says, okay, וכי תימא מעשה שהיה מפני מה לא אסרוה *v'chi
teima ma'ase shehaya mipnei ma lo asruha*, so why was בת שבע
*Batsheva* not forbidden to דוד *David*? I mean, so רש"י *Rashi* says
I don't understand,
where was the where was where was you know where was דוד
*David* making this claim that she was forbidden? So רש"י *Rashi* says
it means because everybody knew that she had slept with דוד *David*,
so that’s a good that’s good enough like two עדים *edim*. Okay,
תוספות *Tosafos* says no, if the whole point is if you say
your wife committed adultery she’s forbidden to you because and we’re going
to we as the בית דין beis din *Beis Din* are going
to
see that through, not let you continue to live with her because
we’re saying according to you she’s forbidden, you can't continue to live
with her. So here תוספות *Tosafos* says the question is so דוד
*David* knew he had committed adultery, so why was דוד *David* allowed
to continue living with her? Right? Assuming דוד *David* was keeping הלכה
*Halacha*, right? So okay, whatever slip-up he had he committed adultery but
why did he keep on living with her afterwards? Right? Because you
because once we say that once from your perspective she’s committed adultery
and we’re going to force you to keep with the הלכה *Halacha*
that you’re claiming applies, right? So the גמרא *Gemara* says so why
did דוד *David* keep on living with her? She should have known
that he had committed adultery, he should be bound by that. So
the גמרא *Gemara* said מפני מה לא אסרוה *mipnei ma lo asruha*,
התם אונס הוה *hasam ones havei*. No, because דוד *David* had forced
her. He didn't like literally like you know he didn't he didn't
actually do you know it wasn't that the act of sex was
through a violent act, but what type of choice did she have?
You know there's different degrees of rape. So what type of choice
did she have? The king says she has to sleep with him.
Okay, so so ah so that's the interesting thing. So the הלכה
*Halacha* that a woman who commits adultery is forbidden to her husband
and to the you know and to the adulterer is only when
it is a willful act, right? Not when it’s a rape. So
the irony is if that if if
this man rapes
a married woman, she's not forbidden to him because the woman didn't
commit willful adultery. You see the irony here? It’s all about the
woman. It's all about the woman betray the wife betraying her husband.
If a wife betrayed her husband and committed willful adultery, she’s forbidden
to her husband and to the man she slept with. If she
was raped, so she didn't commit adultery, she’s not forbidden to her
husband or yeah and she’s not committed to the man who who
forcefully made her have sex, דוד *David*. Okay, because since she did
not commit she did not do anything wrong. And forbidden to either?
Either. So דוד *David* can continue living with her because initially he
had only raped her. Except for כהן *Kohen*, right? Yeah, כהן *Kohen*.
Still a חוטא נזכר *chotei nizkar*? What can I tell you? This
is okay. ואיבעית אימא כי הא דאמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר
רבי יונתן *v'iba'is eima ki ha d'amar Rabi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar
Rabi Yochanan*, כל היוצא *kol hayotzei*, ah maybe we’ll finish the דף
*daf*. If no if there's no more questions we'll finish the דף
*daf*. כל היוצא למלחמת בית דוד גט כריתות כותב לאשתו *kol hayotzei
l'milchemes beis David get krisus kosev l'ishto*. Ah, it wasn't adultery. אוריה
*Uriah* had already given her a גט *get*. Okay, because anybody who
was going out to war would write a גט *get* because they
might not come back. There's an interesting question רש"י *Rashi* says write
a גט *get* because in case they die they didn't want their
wives to be to have to deal with יבום *yibbum* going back
to our previous מסכת *maseches*. But תוספות *Tosafos* says then only the
childless husbands with brothers would write a גט *get*. This says כל
היוצא *kol hayotzei*. So תוספות *Tosafos* says no it’s due to the
עגונה *aguna* issue. The guy doesn't come back and you don't know
what happened to him. So they would write a גט *get*. Okay.
Maybe the גט *get* would be on a תנאי *t'nai* if I
don't come back within a year after the end of the war
or within you know within a week after the end of the
war but everybody would give a גט *get* before they would go
out. They tried to there's talk about instituting this in the Israeli
army. Of course the whole problem you know it’s not a problem
for כהנים *Kohanim* because if the גט *get* is בתנאי *be't'nai* then
if the תנאי *t'nai* isn't מקויים *mekuyam* it never you know took
place but of course let’s say the guy didn't come back you
know and then he came back and the תנאי *t'nai* took place
and she had the גט *get* and then he came back three
years later or something like that something had happened right he was
in captivity or whatever. So then she would anyway. But that's the
story. כל היוצא *kol hayotzei*. So so בת שבע *Batsheva* had a
גט *get* from אוריה *Uriah* and therefore when דוד *David* slept went
and and דוד *David* made sure that אוריה *Uriah* did not in
the end return from the war so the תנאי *t'nai* was fulfilled
in the end. Right? Everybody remember the story? Right? So since the
תנאי *t'nai* was fulfilled retroactively she was divorced from אוריה *Uriah* and
therefore he had never committed adultery. כל היוצא למלחמת בית דוד גט
כריתות כותב לאשתו *kol hayotzei l'milchemes beis David get krisus kosev l'ishto*
דכתיב ואת אחיך תפקד *d'chsiv v'es achecha sifkod*. This is ישי *Yishai*
talking to דוד *David* sending him off to the brothers you know
visit your brothers לשלום *l'shalom* ואת ערובתם תקח *v'es arubasam tikach* and
take their ערובתם *arubasam* normally it means but what does this mean?
מאי ואת ערובתם תקח *mai v'es arubasam tikach*? תני רב יוסף דברים
המעורבין בינו לבינה *tani Rav Yosef devarim ham'uravin beino l'veina*. The things
that bind husband to wife. So take the גטין *getin* from them
that will sever their relationship with their wives you know in case
they never don't return from the battle. And Shaul? Right, so דוד
*David* learned it from שמואל *Shmuel*. תני רב יוסף *Tani Rav Yosef*,
oh we did that. אמר אביי *Amar Abaye*, אבל אנן נמי תנינא
Tanina. *aval anan nami tanina* so back to this question of if
the person is believed to say פתח פתוח pesach patuach *pesach patuach*
to make the wife forbidden to him. אבל אנן נמי תנינא *aval
anan nami tanina* we taught in our משנה *Mishnah*: בתולה נישאת ליום
הרביעי *besula nisais l'yom harvii*, ליום הרביעי אין ליום החמישי לא *l'yom
harvii in l'yom chamishi lo*. So it seems we want him דווקא
*davka* to get married on a... Wednesday and it seems like it's
not just a מנהג but the
גמרא's always been
assuming that this is some type of a תקנה takkana that we're
invested in his ability to bring a court case the next day.
Why are we invested in
his ability to
bring a court case the next day?
So ליום הרביעי אין ליום החמישי לא מה טעמא? L'yom revi'i in
l'yom hamishi lo mah ta'ama? Why? משום איקרורי דעתא. mishum icrurei da'ata.
We don't want him to cool off. But what do we care
if he cools off? ולמאי ul'mai for what purpose? אי למיתב לכתובה?
il'mesiv l'ksuba? Ah, cause if she really wasn't a virgin then he
shouldn't be paying her her כתובה, ksuba her full כתובה ksuba? or
maybe not paying her any כתובה? ksuba We'll worry about that later.
But if it's for financial implications why are we invested in that?
That's his problem. Okay? So cool off, נתיב לה. nesiv lah. You
know, נתיב לה nesiv lah makes a lot of sense, right? Why
should we care, oh let's make it possible to make sure that
he'll be able to deprive her of a כתובה ksubah if she
wasn't a virgin? Like why is that our interest? If he really
cares enough about that come to the court five days later, right?
Why do we have to get you married off Wednesday night to
make sure you'll be able to come to the court the next
day? If it's money it's not our interest. אלא לאוסרה עליו? ela
l'osra alav? It must be that we're concerned that she's not a
virgin and that she has committed adultery and that she's forbidden to
him and therefore we want to handle that case the next day
because we don't want a husband and wife living together if he
actually, if they're forbidden, if she actually did commit adultery. So that's
the only reason we would have made this תקנה. takkana. ודקתני טענה
מאי? v'decatani taina mai? What and what type of claim is he
making when he comes the next morning? לאו דקתני טענת פתח פתוח?
la'av d'catani tainas pesach patuach? Isn't he, that he's making the claim
that he experienced her without like you know as a non-virgin even
though there's nothing concrete but it's he's claiming what his experience was?
לא דקתני טענת דמים. lo d'catani tainas damim. No, that he's saying
there was no blood, that he's saying that there were you know
the witnesses, the guards at the door and there was the sheet
and they came in and they inspected the sheet and there was
no blood. And that's a more concrete claim. So yes you are
right. The משנה's concern that he come to בית דין is a
concern that in case she might have committed adultery we'll be able
to clarify the whole thing or at least we'll make sure that
you know if he's claiming she committed adultery they don't continue living
together because we wouldn't want them living together if you know if
on his own claim you know she committed adultery even if there's
no objective evidence. But that might only be
something that gets off
the ground based on the claim of lack of blood. It might
not get off the ground based on the claim of פתח פתוח
pesach pasuach. because he might not know what he's talking about. But
he's saying פתח פתוח מצאתי? pesach patuach m'tsasi. He's not saying פתח
פתוח מצאתי. pesach patuach matsasi He's saying really לא מצאתי דמים. lo
matsasi damim. Right, meaning what, what is he saying? What do you
mean what is he, you know, Rabbi Elazar says that פתח פתוח
pesach pasuach. מצאתי is believed. The question is what is the, what
are we assuming this whole פרק perek deals with? The guy coming
the next morning and saying she's not a virgin. And the question
is based on what? So Rabbi Elazar is saying based on just
the way he experienced the act of intercourse. And the גמרא is
saying no there's no evidence. Maybe all the cases is he's claiming
she's not a virgin based on the absence of blood. Okay? And
that is something that is more concrete. Okay? So that's basically what
this boils down to. Okay? The whole פרק perek is about he
says she wasn't a virgin, how does he know? So Rabbi Elazar
says he knows just by saying that was my experience during the
act of intercourse. And the גמרא says there's no proof that's the
case. The case might be he said we inspected the sheet there
was no blood. And that certainly is more as the פשט. pshat.
We're going to see there were guards at the door, there was
a special sheet, the whole thing. So let's take a look at
one more. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל האומר פתח פתוח מצאתי נאמן
להפסידה כתובתה. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel Ha'omer pesach patuach matsasi ne'eman
l'hafsideh ksubasah. Now we're moving from the fact that פתח פתוח pesach
pasuach is a legitimate claim or according to Rabbi Elazar a legitimate
claim, you know we don't say he doesn't know what he's talking
about, and we're saying not only does it have the implication to
make her forbidden on him because you're bound by your own statement,
okay, but it actually can directly hurt her. His claim is believed
and therefore she doesn't get her כתובה kesuvah. because now she's not
a virgin. Now this is crazy. Since why, why are you believed?
Right? Then you'll just, then you'll just always say it. Right? I
mean how are you believed to make somebody else lose that money?
Where's the evidence? Where's the proof? It's just your own claim. So
we'll worry about the how in a minute, but let's first read
the גמרא. The גמרא again is going to focus on the question
of פתח פתוח versus טענת דמים. tainas damim. So the גמרא says
אמר רב יוסף מאי קא משמע לן? Amar Rav Yosef mai kamashmalan?
Ah, that's a חידוש? תנינא. האוכל אצל חמיו ביהודה שלא בעדים אינו
יכול לטעון טענת בתולים מפני שמתייחד עמה. Ha'ochel eitzel chamiv b'Yehuda shelo
b'eidim eino yachol liton tainas b'sulim mipnei she'misyached imah. So if somebody
had, you know, ate with his father-in-law in יהודה Yehuda and there
weren't witnesses to chaperone, then he can no longer claim that she
wasn't a virgin the next morning, you know, after the נישואין, right?
Because everybody remember the story in יהודה Yehuda, was that even during,
even at the period of קידושין, they would, they might go together
in the same room and have sex. So if that was possible,
if that had possibly happened, he loses his any, any validity to
his claim after the wedding night that she wasn't a virgin. Cause
it's like "Yeah, good reason she wasn't a virgin, you probably slept
together earlier." Okay. So the גמרא says ביהודה הוא דלא מצי טעין?
B'Yehuda hu delo matsi tayan? So in יהודה Yehudah. he can't claim
that, הא בגליל מצי טעין? ha b'Galil matsi tayan? In גליל Galil
he can claim. ולמאי? ul'mai? Now for what purposes can he say
she's not a virgin? אי לאוסרה עליו, il'osrah alav, ביהודה מאי לא?
b'Yehuda mai lo? If it's just to make her forbidden on him,
so then even in יהודה, Yehudah right, you know, that would work.
But you understand if I'm just hurting myself by my claim... So
what matters? Oh, of course she's not a virgin, he probably slept
with her. Okay, but I'm not trying to hurt her. I mean,
indirectly I'm going to hurt her because I'm going to be forced
to divorce her. But I'm just trying to hurt myself and I'm
saying I didn't sleep with her before the wedding night, and I
slept with her now and she wasn't a virgin. So if that's
my claim, I should be bound by it, even in יהודה. Yehudah.
So if we're saying there's a difference between יהודה Yehudah and גליל,
Galil, we're obviously not talking that I'm coming to hurt myself, we're
coming that I'm trying to hurt her. And therefore my claim is
undermined in יהודה. Yehudah So it can't be לאוסרה עליו. It must
be אלא לאו להפסידה כתובתה. ela lav lehafsidah kesuvatah. I'm trying to
hurt her and say that she's not entitled to her כתובה. kesuvah.
So in יהודה we say, ha, that's not going to be accepted.
Maybe you slept with her already. But in גליל Galil it will
be believed. So we have this idea that a husband's claim is
accepted without any objective evidence to say that his wife isn't a
virgin unless it's in יהודה in order to make her lose her
כתובה. kesuvah? Now why that should be true is crazy, seems to
be crazy because how can you just, you know, on your say
so make her lose her כתובה? kesuvah? Okay, we'll worry about that
in a minute. But right now our question is, on what basis
are you claiming she's not a virgin? והא דקתני טענת מאי? veha
dekateni ta'anat mai? What are you claiming? לאו דקתני טענת פתח פתוח?
lav dekateni ta'anat pesach pasuach? Aren't you claiming because you know the
door was open, you didn't experience any obstruction in the act of
sex? לא דקתני דמים. lo dekateni damim. Back to the other point,
no, it's just saying there was no blood. Okay, so the fact
that this whole פרק perek deals with claiming she wasn't a virgin,
there's no evidence that it's the טענה ta'anah of פתח פתוח. It
might be the more obvious claim of we looked at the sheet
and there was no blood. So before we end, just one statement
about, okay, he says there was no blood, fine. But what, it's
all his own say-so, why is he believed to make her lose
her כתובה? kesuvah? So look at one line in רש״י. Rashi. רש״י
Rashi says, three lines down, no, three lines down, טענת פתח פתוח
מצאתי, ta'anat pesach pasuach matzasi, in the wide lines, דאף על גב
דאין עדים בדבר זה ולא טענה מוכחת. de'af al gav de'ein edim
bedavar zeh velo ta'anah mochachas. There's no witnesses and there's no real,
you know, substantiation of your claim, right? It's not like he says
he brought the sheet and he brought the witnesses. He's just saying
there was no blood. Nevertheless, אלא עלה סמכינן. ela ala samchinan. We
trust him. Why? To make her lose her כתובה? kesuvah. דאמרינן אי
לאו דקושטא הוא, de'amrinan ee lav dekushta hu, if it was not
true, לא היה מפסיד סעודתו. lo hayah mafsid se'udaso. Okay, he would
not have spent all this money on a big wedding feast just
in order to have sex one night and then to say, oh,
she's not a virgin and she doesn't get her כתובה. kesuvah. ואם
היה שונאה מתחילה, היה מתחילה מגרשה ולא טרח בסעודת נישואין. ve'im hayah
sone'ah mitechilah, hayah mitechilah megarshah velo tarach bese'udat nisuin. Okay, so the
fact is we just assume. Now, so meaning, like if he makes
the claim five years into marriage after they've been having a rough
time and he's divorcing her, oh by the way, on her wedding
night she wasn't a virgin, we would laugh him out of the
court case. But if the next morning he's saying it, so then
somehow we say he wouldn't have made all this up, you know,
he wouldn't have gone to all this trouble. I don't exactly fully
understand that because maybe he just wants the wedding but he doesn't
want to pay the full כתובה. kesuvah. But maybe it's not always
an easy middle state to be in because as we're seeing, once
you make that claim, there might be consequences of having to get
a divorce, right? Not just of lowering the amount of the כתובה.
kesuvah, So this is a fascinating thing and this is going to
be really important for the rest of the פרק perek because the
whole פרק perek starts out they're getting married Wednesday night, come to
court the next morning. So the whole point is, well what happens
in the court the next morning? A, what claim is he making?
No blood or פתח פתוח. No blood is the more concrete one.
פתח פתוח is the one that we're claiming might also be good.
And B, even if he makes the claim, it's only his say-so.
What are the implications? So here we say implication number one is
she's forbidden on him, not objectively but because he's bound by it,
at least in certain circumstances based on ספק ספיקא and
so on. So that's that whole question. In most cases no, it's
only very special cases she'd be forbidden on him. And implication number
two is, if what he's saying is true, she loses her כתובה,
kesuvah. either all or part of her כתובה. And somehow it looks
like we're going to believe him even without any supporting evidence. So
all of this is going to be relevant as it plays out
in the rest of the פרק perek about his claims the next
morning. Okay, more to be continued tomorrow.
That's good, we caught up.